In today's video, we're going to talk
about commonly asked questions relating
to ice cream and gelato making at home.
There are a lot of questions that get
asked about people that are new to
making ice cream at home and even those
that are time served and have made ice
cream for years, decades. So, in this
video, I thought I'd go through some of
the most commonly asked questions and
hopefully clear up some of those
questions that you might have. So, the
first section is general ice cream
making. This one comes up a lot and I
had a really interesting slash rude
person comment on what they thought
gelato was. So, what is the difference
between ice cream and gelato?
Ice cream and gelato, there are a couple
of distinct differences. One is the
sugar content. Gelato generally has much
higher sugar levels than American ice
cream. It has lower fat levels. So
gelato has anywhere between generally 6
to 12% fat. And then ice cream or
American style ice cream will have
anywhere from 10% all the way up to 22
or 24% fat. There is also one other
difference that is not very wellnown and
that is the amount of overrun. Gelato
doesn't have as much overrun as
Americanstyle ice cream, but in a home
environment, you can't control that. So,
it's to a degree irrelevant. The next
question is, how do you stop ice cream
going rock hard in your freezer? That is
all about sugars and sugar substitutes.
If you have too much fat in an ice
cream, you can balance that hard result
by increasing the sugar or changing the
freezing point is the more accurate way
to describe stopping something going
hard. So, a freezing point is at what
temperature the ice cream at all the
water freezes solid. So, if you balance
a recipe with a freezing temperature of
or a serving temperature of -7, then
it's likely not going to freeze solid at
all in your home freezer. -7 centigrade.
But if you balance a recipe so that it
has a serving temperature of -10
centigrade, then you'll need to take it
out of your freezer which is at -7
centrade on average and let it come up
to - 10 centigrade. So it's about how
you balance that freezing point of your
ice cream, gelato, sorbet, whatever it
is you're making. You can adjust those
with straight sugar, dextrose,
arythril, alulose, any sugar or sugar
substitute can change your freezing
point of your recipe along with things
like alcohols,
glycerin, these will all change the
freezing point of your ice cream.
Why does homemade ice cream sometimes
get icy? This is a huge question with
loads of different reasons as to why it
generally happens. But in a home
environment, there are a couple of main
reasons why it goes wrong. And that is
that your recipe is not balanced. There
is too much free water in there. That
free water equates to ice, large ice
crystals. And the second is your freezer
and how you're dealing with it. If your
freezer is a frostfree freezer, then it
has a freeze thaw cycle built into it
and your ice cream will melt generally
overnight. Not completely, but it will
melt considerably and then it will
refreeze. That encourages those ice
crystals to get larger and larger and
larger until it's just horrible. Can I
make ice cream without an ice cream
maker? Yes, you absolutely can. No churn
ice cream has been around for donkish
years. It's it's far from a luxury
product because you have to rely on
certain ingredients to get that result.
The biggest problem with no churn ice
cream is the amount of sugar that it
needs to create the result that you
want. If you're one of these people that
doesn't like putting any sugar in
recipes, you're going to struggle
because it you've then lost a balance of
solids and sugars or sugar substitutes
to create the effect that you want. It
is doable and you can create a nice ice
cream using no churn methods, but it is
far and away from the luxury product
that that we are able to achieve with an
ice cream machine, even a ninja creamy
style machine as well. But in a future
video, I will show you how to make the
best no churn ice cream that you will
ever make. And it's not using the same
method that most people will teach you.
So stick around for that one. And the
last one in the general ice cream making
section is
what is the secret to getting super
creamy texture in your homemade ice
cream. That is again a huge subject but
generally it is the amount of solids in
your ice cream. Those solids usually
come from milk. So milk solids, milk
fat, dairy fat, butter fat. That will
have a huge impact on the creamy mouth
feel of your ice cream. But you do have
to make sure that your recipe is
balanced. I say that a lot, but it's
super important. The next section is
ingredients and science.
I get asked this one at least twice a
week. Is why, Nick? Why do you use eggs
in some recipes and not in others? I
generally don't use a lot of eggs in my
recipes because if you use too many egg
yolks, you're tasting egg. that's that's
the flavor that you're actually getting
and it starts to muddy the flavors that
you're trying to create. So, if you're
making a strawberry ice cream, you use
egg yolks, then you're you're actually
making a strawberry and egg flavored ice
cream. It's a really quick and easy way
to muddy a lot of flavors. So, I
generally don't use a lot of eggs. I
also find it quite wasteful. The egg
whites are left over. I know you can use
egg whites for lots of things and I do,
but I generally find using the
scientific approach to ice cream a much
more pleasing result for me. The flavors
are true and strong and it's much easier
to make. What does malt powder do in ice
cream? Now, considering I've only done
about four or five molted flavors, it it
comes up a lot. This malt is just or
malt extract is just another type of
sugar. It's it it's a way to bring these
deep flavors from the malt into your ice
cream base, but they do act just like
normal sugar in your ice cream. So, you
must account for that. If you've never
had a molted vanilla milkshake, you got
to try it. It's delicious.
So, have a go at making a molted ice
cream. Whether that be with dry malt
extract powder or malt extract liquid,
give one of those a try. It's delicious.
How do stabilizers actually work? Huge
question. Can't answer that in this
video, but everyone is slightly
different as to what it does. But if you
look at it as a general term, what a
stabilizer does is it grabs hold of any
remaining water that is going to turn
into a large ice crystal and turns it
into either a gel or it just increases
the viscosity which means it makes it
thicker. That then gives you a better
mouth feel and the ice crystals are much
smaller which gives you again a much
more luxurious kind of ice cream
texture. Is there a big difference
between using fresh fruit and fruit
puree? Yes, there is a big big
difference. Fresh fruit has a lot of
water in it. So, you need to cook some
of that out or account for it in your
recipes. Fruit purees have already had a
lot of that water dealt with and removed
during the making of it. So, you don't
have to worry about that so much. If you
look at things like strawberries,
there's so much water in there that if
you take 200 g worth of fresh
strawberries, about 175 g, that's water.
So when you put that into an ice cream,
you're just adding the potential for
large ice crystals, which is why
strawberry ice cream can get, you know,
really icy. So you need to account for
that. You need to cook that down, remove
some of that water, and stabilize your
recipe. You can use milk powders to
stabilize that recipe. Doesn't have to
be stabilizer. It can just be something
like milk powder. So that's a great way
to to look at it. You can also use jams
and jellies and marmalades to flavor ice
creams. Something to remember when
making fruit flavored ice creams is
you're adding fruit to dairy. So you are
not getting a fruit sorbet super strong
kind of flavor, you are getting a milky
version of it cuz you're adding it to
milk. So if you're if you're adding
strawberries to to milk, you're getting
like strawberry milkshake kind of
flavor. You're not getting strawberry
strong flavor like you would do in a
sorbet. Uh, lastly in the ingredient
section is, can I use nondairy milk to
make ice cream that is still creamy?
Yes, you absolutely can. I recommend
cashew milk because the amount of solids
that are in it really help boost the
creamy texture of ice cream. Things like
almond milk, it is ultra low in solids
and will generally just result in a
pretty crappy ice cream. So, oat milk,
again, all of these are subjective to
the brand that you buy. Some are much
better than others, but as a generalized
whole, cashew milk is the one to go for
if you want to do it. If you can't, then
you have to balance the recipe with
other means. Onto the next section,
which is flavors and recipes.
Nick, what is your most popular flavor
you have ever made? And that is my
double dark chocolate cookie, which is
two different types of chocolate. a dark
chocolate fudge with Oreos added in or
chocolate cookies added in. It's always
a winner. Sells out basically
everywhere. Um, it's one of those
flavors that every customer that I have,
I I design ice cream flavors for
companies and businesses as well. They
always want this one because it's got
this reputation as being a quick seller.
It sells out everywhere. But to be fair,
I've made a lot of really good ice
creams. Do you have a goto recipe base
that works with everything? No. Doesn't
exist. Just doesn't exist. You can't.
There is no catch all. There is no one
recipe that works for everything.
Unfortunately, all chocolate recipes are
very different to vanilla recipes cuz
chocolate has a lot more solids,
increased sometimes increased sugar,
increased fat as well. All fruit water
content is different. So, you have to
wait for that. There's no catch all
version of a recipe for ice cream or
gelato, I'm afraid. So, that's just a
no. How do you come up with your unique
flavors? I don't know. I just kind of
do. I guess I'm one of those people that
just likes to try new things, mix
flavors together, see what the result
is. Sometimes good, sometimes the bad.
But I generally don't put the bad ones
on on here. What's the point of that?
It's um it's just experiment with
whatever flavors you like. If you like
flavor A and flavor B, stick it
together. See what happens. What is the
weirdest ice cream flavor that I have
ever tried to make? The weirdest ice
cream flavor. I did a black garlic ice
cream years ago. And actually, that was
really nice. And then I did a super dark
like a black cocoa ice cream with 100%
chocolate and it was so bitter that it
was it was pretty rank. But weird is, I
guess, subjective to personal taste.
What's weird to one is not weird to
another. you know, uh, uh, flavors or
popular flavors in something like China
and Japan and Korea would be very
different to the kind of flavors that
you would want to find in the Midwest of
the USA. So, it it's kind of subjective.
Cheese probably. Uh, I did craft cheese
ice cream. That was rank.
Which chocolate works best in ice cream?
Milk, dark, or white?
Uh, again, it's whatever flavor you
want. White chocolate ice cream is
delicious. Really, really nice. Can be a
little bit sweet, so you have to kind of
balance that sugar level out. Milk and
dark chocolate. Milk chocolate is you
have to be careful using milk chocolate
in ice cream because the flavor is quite
weak. So, you need to make sure that you
boost it with um you know, cocoa powders
and balance that flavor out like a dair
I did a dairy milk ice cream or years
ago. One of one of the first ones I ever
made. Uh, and it was delicious because
there's so much going on in there that
it really enabled that Cadbury chocolate
flavor to come through and a a English
Cadbury chocolate flavor, not a copycat
Cadbury flavor. Um, so milk and milk and
dark chocolate, you have to kind of play
with the flavor that you want to get.
White chocolate, again, not all white
chocolate is the same, but it is quite
sweet and it can go quite cold white
chocolate. Uh, and that is just due to
the amount of fat that generally is in
there. It's a different type of fat. So,
cocoa butter on its own produces a
colder ice cream. Practical questions
and behind the scenes,
how long does it actually take you to
film and edit a video filming? Uh it
does depend on the on the recipe that
I'm doing. But if it's a churned ice
cream, then you have the day one when I
will actually film them the combining of
the quick intro, then combining of the
ingredients, and then from there I will
um heat it up, cook it, and then chill
it down. I like to let the flavors
mellow in the refrigerator for at least,
you know, four to 12 hours. So that
moves on to day two. Day two is then
churn. If I do that first thing in the
morning, then I can dish up and eat it
at the end of the day. So that's day
two, two days. If for some reason the
churn happens later in the second day,
then that moves on to 3 days. So it's
quite a long process. Ninja Creamy,
depending on the recipe, if it's a no
cook, you can you can get it, freeze it
in one day, and process it and eat it
all by the second morning. So you still
roll over into day two, but it's um it's
generally a bit quicker. Editing can
take forever depending on the video.
That's down to personal skill, I guess,
preference and experience. I've been
making these videos for years now. So,
as a whole, it takes about 4 days to
make a video, but not back to back. It
just spans four four days, and each day
has a section dedicated to making these
videos for you.
What camera or setup do you use to shoot
your ice cream videos? I use a Fuji XT3
with a top mounted screen and I use a 12
mm lens Samyang lens which is a manual
focus. I also use my phone which is an
iPhone 12 Pro still still on the 12. I
don't want to update it. I don't need to
update it but it I use that for a lot of
the other shots as well. I am going to
start changing the way I film and
hopefully give you a better aesthetic to
the videos coming up soon. So that
that's what I use. I also have this
ginormous light here which is a 100 W go
do light with a softbox
uh foldable softbox on top of it. The
camera stood on a tripod. Lots of kind
of add-ons. And this is a road wireless
mic or wireless goto I think is the
actual name of it. Um, and then I use
Road's official
uh lav lab mic addition to that. Just
makes it a little bit nicer and you
don't have the the microphone stuck in
here. Sometimes I forget and you know,
you've seen it, I'm sure.
If you hear a clicking, it's actually
the oven. I'm making yogurt coming in a
video in a couple of weeks. Or yogurt,
depending on where you are. Do you eat
all the ice cream you make on the
channel? No, I absolutely do do not. I
do eat quite a bit, but I we limit in
this household, we limit our ice cream
consumption to Fridays, Saturdays, and
Sundays only. Generally Fridays and
Saturdays, cuz otherwise you're looking
at three out of seven days too much. So,
we will just have a serving of ice cream
or usually a large serving on Friday or
Saturday and then a little tiny bit on
Sunday if we're feeling naughty. Um, but
no, I I give a lot of the ice cream away
I make here at home on the channel to
neighbors and friends.
How do you store all that ice cream
without it going bad? I have a
designated chest freezer down in the
basement. Um, chest freezers are much
better. This is a non frostfree chest
freezer. That's important. Um, chest
freezers are much better cuz cold air
sinks, hot air rises. So, if you got a
door chest a door freezer, when you open
that, all the cold air comes bellowing
out and then the warmer air goes in the
top. And then when you close the door,
it creates that kind of vacuum suction
that you hear and has to bring all that
down to the minus7 C give or take that
your freezer is set to. If you have a
chest freezer, all that cold air stays
inside. So when you take things out, it
you're only losing a little bit as you
create that kind of pull of air taking
things out of it. Um then when you close
it down, there's a much smaller amount
of warm air trapped in the top that then
has to be processed and turned into cold
air. So, it's much more efficient. Um,
and also nonrost free. So, if your
freezer is a frostfree one, then it will
thaw every night or every two nights and
then refreeze again. It won't thaw
completely, but it will go right up to
like minus 5. So, your ice cream starts
to defrost. Ignore that in the
background. Your ice cream will start to
defrost and then freeze again. Creates
huge ice crystals. So, it's a big
problem. If you've got ice cream in your
freezer at home and it's going icy, just
check on that. Most modern freezers,
fridge freezer combos are frost free. So
that that has a huge impact. If you're
serious about ice cream making, Costco,
they got like chest freezers for less
than $100. Um, in the UK, you can get
them for, you know, not a lot of money,
50, 60 quid, something like that. Uh,
finally in the behind the scenes and
practical section is if someone is just
starting out, what's the easiest recipe
to try first? Easiest recipe is just
straight vanilla. Uh you can if if you
really want to go super simple then try
something like the cookies and cream no
churn try something like pistachio any
of those simple ingredients don't use
stabilizers or egg yolks they are philly
style so just dairy and then your
flavorings with sugar it's super super
in super easy to do you can do the um
fur de latte which is unflavored so
dairy f it's milk flavored gelato that's
um I'm going to do that on the channel
as well. I get asked for that all the
time, so I should really do that. Uh,
but start with a basic vanilla. Just use
extract and you will be fine. I'm here
to give you tips and tricks and help you
along your way and make sure whatever
style of ice cream you make, whether
that is ultra highfat US style ice cream
to super dense fudgy Italian gelato to
bright, strong flavored sorbos, zero
sugar ice creams. Use the knowledge
that's here on this channel to make your
journey a bit better, make your ice
cream a little bit better. And if you've
got questions, ask. I try to get all to
the comments, but I get so many comments
now that it's quite difficult for me to
keep up with answering them, but I do my
best. You can join me on Patreon and ask
away. I've got some classes that I will
be uploading to my website, which will
start going through some complicated
elements of ice cream making that are
relevant to homemakers that are serious
about making it and commercial ice cream
makers, too. So I think the first one is
going to go live in the next two weeks.
I will put a link in the description
below so you can check that out. And
these are deep master classes for some
very specific elements of making ice
cream. So there we go. It's uh that's
what's that I don't know 5 10 20 FAQs
for making ice cream at home. If you
have any more questions on the subject,
feel free to politely reach out and I
will see you next week.